Guide to the Leavitt farm and family papers, circa 1911-1978
Leavitt farm and family papers,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Leavitt farm and family papers, 1911-1978
8583
Leavitt family. Leavitt family
4 Cubic Feet.
Correspondence, Diaries, Financial Records.}
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection contains documentation of the Leavitt farm, primarily bills, invoices and receipts.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
The Leavitt family began farming and raising crops near Gabriels in 1888, when Lyman Leavitt moved from Bloomingdale. However, the deed for the farm was not registered until 1890. His son, Arthur, joined him after taking ''short courses'' at Cornell University. Around 1915, Arthur Leavitt took over the farm. Potatoes and seed potatoes were the main crops. There was only enough livestock to meet the needs of farming (work horses) and the family (a milk cow and a beef cow). In 1937, Arthur purchased a large barn from the Rockefellers at Bay Pond, dismantled it, and brought it to Gabriels. He also bought a small barn, which he used to store pieces of the larger barn over the winter, and then in 1938 erected what became known as The Big Barn. In 1939, Arthur's son, William, completed his education at Cornell University and joined in farming with his father. In 1976, Leavitt Farms was incorporated. Between 1920 and 1980 the farm grew to approximately 700 acres, harvesting 400 +/- acres of potatoes. William married Lenore Newell from Keeses' Mills (daughter of Pauline and Harold Newell). William and Lenore had three boys: Robert, Arthur and David. For a short period of time, all three sons farmed in Gabriels. David left to teach and then do administrative work in NYS Dept. of Corrections. In 1997, potato growing ceased when Robert and his wife, Mary Lou, left to start their own farm up north in Churubusco. Arthur remained on the farm taking care of other crops and developing a gravel mine on the property. In 2015, Ralph Child, scion of another well-known potato farming family in Franklin County, bought a large portion of Leavitt farm and returned it to potato growing. Arthur continues to grow hay and sell gravel and stone.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection contains documentation of the Leavitt farm, primarily bills, invoices and receipts.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Leavitt family.; Leavitt, Arthur.; Leavitt, David.; Leavitt, Lyman.; Leavitt, Robert.; Leavitt, William.
Subjects:
Agriculture.; Agriculture; Potatoes.; Potatoes -- Equipment and supplies.
Places:
New York (State)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Receipts and Invoices
Boxes 2-3
Alpha Order
Chronological Order
Series II. Ledgers
Box 4
Series III. Administrative Records
Box 1
Series IV. Course Materials
Box 1
CONTAINER LIST
- Receipts and Invoices, 1910-1978
  - Alpha Order, 1910-1929, 1942-1946, 1955-1959, 1972-1978
    - A-B, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - C-D (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - E-F, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - G-H, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - I-J, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - K-L, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - M (1-2), 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
    - N-O (1-3), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - P-Q, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - R-S, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - T-U (1-2), 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
    - A, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - B, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - C, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - D, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - E, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - F, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - G, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - H, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - I-J, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - K, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - L, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - M, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - N, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - O-Q, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - R, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - S, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - T, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - V, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - W-Y, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - A, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - B, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - C, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - D, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - F, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - G, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - H, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - I-J, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - K, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - L, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - M, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - N, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - O, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - P-Q, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - R-S, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - T, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - U-V, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - W-Z, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Chronological Order, 1910-1959
    - Receipts and Invoices, 1910-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1-21)
- Ledgers, 1910-1969 (Box 4)
- Correspondence and Administrative Records, 1916-1975
  - Correspondence, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Voter Ballot, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Inspection certificates, 1917-1927, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Saranac Lake Lodge, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - List of growers, prices, stock, and buyers, 1921-1925 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - National League of Commission Merchants, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Tags, 1925-1951 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Tax records, 1943-1971 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Plot maps, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Potato crops, 1954-1975 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bills, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Catalogs and instruction books, Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Inspection report template, letter to Santa Claus, Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Course Materials
  - Cornell report card, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - An. Hus. 20 Genetics, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Farm Management 102 course material, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Farm Management 102 exams and assignments, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Botany 1 Laboratory outlines, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Botany 1 evaluations, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Botany 1, Rural Ed., English 2, and Chemistry class notes, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Geology 100 Lab, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Farm Management 102, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Ag Economics 142 lecture notes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ag Economics 142 labs, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ag Economics 142 labs and assigments, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Class notes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Forestry 1 class notes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Economics 1 class notes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meteorology lab, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Geology 100, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alpha Gamma Rho fraternity materials, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Carlot shipments of fruits and vegetables, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - R.S.O. 121, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lab experiment guidelines, Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Agronomy 11 Lab material, Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Agronomy grains and seeds, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bill's Alpha Gamma Rho blazer, Undated; MU-1914 (Box 1)